<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-26T11:31:05+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Oberth Effect</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/oberth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Oberth Effect"/><published>2022-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/oberth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/oberth/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="maths">Maths</h2> <p>The Oberth effect maximises the efficiency of a rocket burn by considering the instantaneous kinetic energy of the rocket at particular moments during its flight and selecting the most suitable time to burn. This concept can be understood by analysing the equation for the kinetic energy of a body at a given instantaneous moment.</p> \[\Delta KE = {1/2} m v^2\] <p>Now, the change in kinetic energy between two instantaneous moments (e.g., from beginning to the end of a burn) can be expressed.</p> \[\Delta KE = {KE}_2 - {KE}_1\] <p>Also assuming that the change in mass of the craft is negligible (i.e., \({m_1} \approx {m_2} \approx m\))</p> \[\Delta KE = {1/2} m ( {v_2}^2 - {v_1}^2 )\] <p>Now, taking the value \({1/2} m\) as an arbitrary scalar, the function above can be graphed in 3D as shown below<d-footnote>https://www.math3d.org/</d-footnote>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-1400.webp"/> <img src="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-1400.webp"/> <img src="/me/assets/img/oberth/oberth_graph_straight.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Three dimensional graph of the change in kinetic energy with respect to the speed of the object before and after an engine burn. </div> <p>As illustrated above, for a constant change of velocity (i.e., constant \(\Delta v = v_2 - v_1\) where \(v_2 &gt; v_1\)), the change in kinetic energy is greatest when the individual values of \(v_1\) and \(v_2\) are larger. For example, let the change in velocity be \(\Delta v = 1 {m/s}\) (assume unit mass of 1 kg). If the initial velocity is \(1 {m/s}\) and the final velocity is \(2 {m/s}\), the change in kinetic energy is \(3J\). However, if the initial velocity is \(2 {m/s}\) and the final velocity is \(3 {m/s}\), the change in kinetic energy is \(5J\). This example shows that equal changes in velocity with different starting conditions can produce different changes in kinetic energy (i.e., \(3J\) compared to \(5J\)). That is, a greater change in kinetic energy is possible, using the same change in velocity, when the change in velocity occurs at higher values. In summary, for a fixed amount of rocket fuel (i.e., fixed change in velocity, \(\Delta v\)), a greater change in overall kinetic energy of the rocket can be achieved by beginning the burn at a higher initial velocity.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <p>On 25 December, 2021 at 1:20pm ACDT, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) launched from French Guiana aboard the Ariane 5 launch vehicle. However, at about T+08m:04s, the rocket and payload began losing altitude as shown in the altitude vs. distance travelled graph below<d-footnote>NASA (2021) James Webb Space Telescope Launch — Official NASA Broadcast Dec 25, 2021. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7nT7JGZMbtM&amp;t=6710s&amp;ab_channel=NASA (Accessed: Jan 03, 2022).</d-footnote>. By losing altitude, the craft traded some gravitational potential energy for some extra kinetic energy - increasing its speed. Now at a higher initial velocity than it would have been without the energy trade, the rocket began burning its engines for a specific change in velocity. The total kinetic energy increase was more efficient due to the engine burn at higher initial speed (Oberth effect). Utilising the Oberth effect, the Ariane 5 achieved such a fuel efficient payload orbit injection that the JWST now has significantly more propellant than expected to sustain its exploration mission. This extra propellant is expected to extend the lifetime of the JWST far beyond its initially expected 10 years.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/jwst_oberth-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/jwst_oberth-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/me/assets/img/oberth/jwst_oberth-1400.webp"/> <img src="/me/assets/img/oberth/jwst_oberth.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Altitude versus curvilinear distance for the launch of the James Webb Space Telescope. </div>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="astrodynamics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why going down first helps you go higher.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Size of the Observable Universe</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/size-universe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Size of the Observable Universe"/><published>2022-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/size-universe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/me/blog/2022/size-universe/"><![CDATA[<p>The size of the observable universe is a more complex idea than it appears at face value. It is widely known that the universe is approximately 13.8 billion years old. From this knowledge, it is logical to assume our observable universe is 13.8 billion light years in radius in all directions. However, our true observable universe is approximately 46.5 billion light years in radius (or about 93 billion light years in diameter). The reason for this discrepancy in initial logic (13.8 Bly) and scientific fact (46.5 Bly) is due to a battle between light and space.</p> <h2 id="an-expanding-observable-universe">An Expanding Observable Universe</h2> <p>Lets assume our universe is a flat piece of latex placed on a table. Now assume we paint galaxies on the piece of latex and that their motion <i>through/on</i> the paper is too miniscule to notice. Watching the universe from our perspective, continuous emissions of light from these galaxies are travelling through the universe at a fixed speed (the speed of light). Using this idea, it’s reasonable to imagine an imaginary circle around each galaxy which represents the visible range around that galaxy. That is, light can only travel so far in the time it has been given to travel (i.e., since we painted them on the latex) - and hence as time continues, this visible range of each galaxy grows at the speed of light. This expansion of visible range, due to the fixed speed of light and continuous flow of time, implies that more and more of the universe becomes visible with time - i.e., an expanding observable universe.</p> <h2 id="a-contracting-observable-universe">A Contracting Observable Universe</h2> <p>The reason why the true size of the observable universe is larger than the expected value of 13.8 Bly in radius is because the universe is expanding (discovered by Edwin Hubble in 1929). This rate of expansion, over the 13.8 billion year age of the universe equates to about 33 billion light years of additional space in all directions. Thus, the true size of our visible universe is approximately 13.8+33 Bly = 46.8 Bly in radius<d-footnote>Encyclopedia Brittanica (2013) Know about the concept of the observable universe and on measuring the observable universe within the whole universe Feb 26, 2013. Available At: https://www.britannica.com/video/185400/universe (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022).</d-footnote>. Importantly, this expansion occurs everywhere in the universe as it expands into itself. Referring to the latex universe analogy, this could be represented as stretching the latex - the galaxies aren’t moving (remember our assumption from earlier) but the space between them is expanding. The effect of an expanding universe is contrary to its name as it pushes galaxies apart - reducing their observable regions. Additionally, the rate of expansion exceeds the speed of light - meaning that even though the universe is physically becoming larger, galaxies are being pushed further apart and hence our observable region is becoming smaller.</p> <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2> <p>The rate of the expansion of space exceeds the speed of light. Therefore, even though the universe is becoming physically larger due to its expansion, this also causes galaxies to be pushed further apart faster than their light travels to each other. Therefore, our observable universe is becoming smaller, but the space it occupies is becoming larger.</p> <h2 id="extra-reading">Extra Reading</h2> <p>The real kicker of this concept is that the expansion of the universe is accelerating (2011 Novel Prize in Physics: Saul Perlmutter, Brian Schmidt, Adam Reiss). Therefore, there will come a time (and a distance away from us), where galaxies at that distance are moving away from us (due to the expansion of space between us and them) faster than the speed of light. When this occurs, the light from such galaxies will slowly dim into nothingness and they will be lost to us forever (assuming the universe never begins contracting).</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="astrodynamics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A battle between light and space.]]></summary></entry></feed>