<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-09-04T18:17:49+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Rockets vs Lightning</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/rockets-vs-lightning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rockets vs Lightning"/><published>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/rockets-vs-lightning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/rockets-vs-lightning/"><![CDATA[<p>After United Launch Alliance’s successful launch of their Vulcan Centaur rocket on the 8th of January, curious eyes may wonder why the rocket is surrounded by four large towers. In fact, if you are a regular observer of rocket launches, you may notice similar towers surrounding rockets at launch pads around the world.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/rockets_vs_lightning/Vulcan_Centaur-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/rockets_vs_lightning/Vulcan_Centaur-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/rockets_vs_lightning/Vulcan_Centaur-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/rockets_vs_lightning/Vulcan_Centaur.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Lift-off of the Vulcan Centaur on January 8, 2024, by United Launch Alliance (ULA). Photo credit: NASASpaceflight<d-footnote>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rtPoAUuYXHo&amp;t=5449s&amp;ab_channel=NASASpaceflight</d-footnote>. </div> <p>Read the full article on IET’s EngX site <a href="https://engx.theiet.org/b/blogs/posts/rockets-vs-lightning">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="aerospace"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is the purpose of the towers surrounding a launch pad.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reviewing ‘Helgoland: The Strange and Beautiful Story of Quantum Physics’</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/book-helgoland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reviewing ‘Helgoland: The Strange and Beautiful Story of Quantum Physics’"/><published>2024-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/book-helgoland</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2024/book-helgoland/"><![CDATA[<p><b>7/10</b></p> <p>‘Helgoland’ expertly brings you into the microcosm of some of the smartest minds the world has ever seen, and guides you through why quantum mechanics is so notoriously nonintuitive. This approach is a refreshing change to most other literature around this topic which tries, and often fails, to explain quantum mechanics itself. Technical notes are quick and concise, never delving too deep such that you lose understanding, nor too brief that you can’t fully appreciate the significance of these discoveries. The main takeaway of the book being that reality is based on the relationships between different things, not necessarily the search for more and more fundamental building blocks. If you enjoy philosophy, the book also delves deeply into this towards the end.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="quantum-mechanics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Difficult to not read in a single sitting.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hubble Constant</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-hubble-constant/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hubble Constant"/><published>2022-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-hubble-constant</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-hubble-constant/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/hubble_constant/thumb_hubble_const-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/hubble_constant/thumb_hubble_const-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/hubble_constant/thumb_hubble_const-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/hubble_constant/thumb_hubble_const.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The expanding universe<d-footnote>https://www.livescience.com/hubble-constant.html</d-footnote>. </div> <p>In the 1920’s Edwin Hubble discovered that the universe is expanding by noticing that the vast majority of galaxies were receding from us (by measuring their distance using <a href="https://patrickcap.github.io/me/blog/2022/tutorial-universal-measuring-sticks/">universal measuring sticks</a> and their redshift) and that more distant galaxies were receding faster. The Hubble constant is a measurement of the rate of this expansion.</p> <h2 id="traditional-measurement-methods">Traditional Measurement Methods</h2> <p>The Hubble constant has traditionally been measured in two ways: using supernovae in distant galaxies to measure their distance, or the fluctuations in the Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation (CMBR). Using the supernova method, calculations of the Hubble constant are about 68 km/s/Mpc (units: kilometres per second per mega-parsec) whilst the CMBR method produced a result of about 72 km/s/Mpc c<d-footnote>Warren, S., 2022. The Hubble constant, explained. [online] News.uchicago.edu. Available at: [Accessed 22 July 2022].</d-footnote> - a significant discrepancy. Note that the units of the Hubble constant indicate a rate of expansion for a particular distance from an observer, the further the distance between two points, the greater the rate of expansion between them.</p> <h2 id="a-new-light">A New Light</h2> <p>In 2010, Wendy Freedman and Barry Madore proposed a new method of measuring the Hubble constant that makes use of red giants: bloated and dying stars. During their final death throes, red giants rapidly increase their core temperature to about 100 million degrees and reduce their overall brightness c<d-footnote>Warren, S., 2022. The Hubble constant, explained. [online] News.uchicago.edu. Available at: [Accessed 22 July 2022].</d-footnote>. Red giants at known distances can be used to calibrate this pattern to be applied to red giants at unknown distances - thus helping to measure the recession rate of a greater sample of galaxies in our universe. This method produced a Hubble constant value of about 69.8 km/s/Mpcd is improving confidence in the true value of the expansion rate of our universe at about 70 km/s/Mpc<d-footnote>Freedman, W. and Madore, B., 2010. The Hubble Constant. [online] Ned.ipac.caltech.edu. Available at: [Accessed 22 July 2022].</d-footnote> - almost splitting the middle between the two previous results.</p> <h2 id="a-new-wave">A New Wave</h2> <p>Even more recently, in 2017, the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory (LIGO) in Livingstone, Louisiana, observed the gravitational wave and electromagnetic aftershock of a collision between two orbiting neutron stars about 120 million years ago/light-years away. Using both of these results, researchers were able to calculate a new value for the Hubble constant at about 70 km/s/Mpc<d-footnote>Warren, S., 2022. The Hubble constant, explained. [online] News.uchicago.edu. Available at: [Accessed 22 July 2022].</d-footnote>. This result strongly agrees with the red giant method found by Freedman and Madore in 2010 and is improving confidence in the true value of the expansion rate of our universe at about 70 km/s/Mpc<d-footnote>Freedman, W. and Madore, B., 2010. The Hubble Constant. [online] Ned.ipac.caltech.edu. Available at: [Accessed 22 July 2022].</d-footnote>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="astronomy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Blowing up the universe like a balloon.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Black Holes, Quasars, and Blazars</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-black-holes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Black Holes, Quasars, and Blazars"/><published>2022-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-black-holes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-black-holes/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/thumb_blazar-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/thumb_blazar-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/thumb_blazar-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/thumb_blazar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Blazar<d-footnote>https://www.wired.com/story/whats-a-blazar-a-galactic-bakery-for-cosmic-rays/</d-footnote>. </div> <p>Black holes are some of the simplest objects in the universe with only three properties: mass, spin, and charge. Mass generally divides the very small (stellar) from the very large (supermassive), spin divides the rotating (likely ubiquitous) from the non-rotating (likely purely hypothetical), and charge divides those that have accreted more protons (positive) from those that have accreted more electrons (negative). Quasars and blazars result from black holes depending on their mass and level of activity.</p> <h2 id="mass">Mass</h2> <p>It is generally believed that there are two main types of black holes when categorised by their mass: stellar and supermassive. Stellar black holes are remnants of large stars (3-10 solar masses) that go supernova and then proceed to collapse into a singularity under their own weight. Whilst stellar black holes are difficult to detect (due to them not emitting light and occassionally forming visible accretion disks), there is an estimated ten million to one billion of them in the Milky Way (compared to the estimation of about 100 billion stars in the Milky Way) <d-footnote>Bolles, D., 2022. Black Holes | Science Mission Directorate. [online] Science.nasa.gov. Available at: [Accessed 20 July 2022]. </d-footnote>.</p> <p>Supermassive blackholes have masses ranging from millions to billions of solar masses and they exist in the centre of the vast majortiy of galaxies <d-footnote>Bolles, D., 2022. Black Holes | Science Mission Directorate. [online] Science.nasa.gov. Available at: [Accessed 20 July 2022]. </d-footnote>. The method of their formation is not yet known perfectly. Some theories suggest that supermassive black holes are seeded from supermassive stars which become extremely large stellar black holes, which then proceeds to grow as it feeds on an abundance of primordial galactical gas. Other theories suggest that they form as a result of many stellar black holes combining or that some black holes exhibit faster rates of growth than others. The Event Horizon Telescope (a network of telescopes spread over the Earth’s surface) has successfully “photographed” two supermassive blackholes: the first being that within the galaxy Messier 81 (M81) which is active and readily observable, the second being that within our own galaxy, the Milky Way, known as Sagittarius A* (pronounded “Sagittarius A star”) (Figures 1 and 2).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/m87_Sastar-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/m87_Sastar-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/m87_Sastar-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/m87_Sastar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Images from the Event Horizont Telescope of the black holes within galaxies Messier 81 (left) and the Milky Way (Sagittarius A*) (right)<d-footnote>Boumann, K., Akiyama, K., Gómez, J.L., 2022. Spot the difference: Imaging Sagittarius A* and M87*. Available at: [Accessed 21 July 2022].</d-footnote>. </div> <h3 id="quasars">Quasars</h3> <p>A quasar (short for quasi-stellar radio source) is a term used to describe active galactic nuclei - that is, supermassive black holes at the centre of galaxies that are feeding on matter and therefore emitting a significant amount of radiation. These luminous structures include an accretion disk emitting visible and ultraviolet light, jets of radio light all the way through to X-ray light are aligned with the axis of rotation of the black hole, and the gas and dust surrounding the black hole shine in infrared light (Figure 2)<d-footnote>Young, M., 2021. What Is a Quasar?. [online] Sky &amp; Telescope. Available at: [Accessed 20 July 2022].</d-footnote>. The jet of a quasar also contains matter such as protons, electrons, and neutrinos (uncharged and very low mass particles) which are accelerated to near luminal velocities from magnetic fields concentrated on the poles of the host black hole.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: The structure of a quasar<d-footnote>Antonucci, R., 2022. The glowing dusty heart of a hidden quasar. Nature 602, 390-391 (2022). doi: https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-022-00380-4</d-footnote>. </div> <h3 id="blazars">Blazars</h3> <p>A blazar is simply a quasar that happens to have its jets pointed towards Earth (Figure 3). Whilst quasars can still be slightly difficult to observe, blazars are much easier to identify as they are some of the most luminous objects in the universe due to their special orientation. As aforementioned, the jets of active galactic nuclei also contain matter such as electrons, protons, and neutrinos moving at near luminal velocities. When considering a blazar, these particles are incident on the Earth, and some experiments such as the IceCube Neutrino Observatory in Antarctica are designed to detect the incident neutrinos from blazars.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar_vs_blazar-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar_vs_blazar-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar_vs_blazar-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/black_holes_quasars_blazars/quasar_vs_blazar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 3: Comparison of active galactic nuclei that point their jets away from Earth (quasar) (left) or towards the Earth (blazar) (right)<d-footnote>Carlson, E., 2018. Blazars explained. [online] Astronomy.com. Available at: [Accessed 20 July 2022].</d-footnote>. </div> <h2 id="spin">Spin</h2> <p>Black holes form by the collapse of matter to a singularity, and since almost all gravitationally bound objects exhibit some angular momentum, it is highly likely that a black hole will also exhibit angular momentum. Furthermore, since black holes form from objects that were once much bigger (e.g., large stars), their rate of rotation also increases as the radius of the object decreases before the black hole is formed (in the same way that an ice skaters rate of rotation increases as they pull their arms towards their body - conservation of angular momentum). Due to this, black holes can spin at rates approaching the speed of light. For example, the black hole Cygnus X-1 (in constellation Cygnus) was measured to have a rate of rotation of about 800 times per second, and with a radius of only 44km<d-footnote>Today's Science. 2022. Cygnus X-1 mass and spin determined. [online] Available at: [Accessed 21 July 2022].</d-footnote> would have points on its event horizon moving at about 74% the speed of light.</p> <p>In such conditions, the effects of frame dragging - when a massive body (which naturally distorts the fabric of spacetime as General Relativity states) moves through or rotates within spacetime, causing the fabric to be dragged with the object. In 2012 and 2022, the Italian Space Agency launched the Laser Relativity Satellite (LARES) 1 and 2, respectively, with the intention of measuring frame dragging caused by Earth.</p> <h2 id="charge">Charge</h2> <p>As mentioned at the start of this page, black holes can become charged by accreting more positively charged matter than negatively charged matter, or vice versa. However, charged black holes are unlikely to occur in nature as once the black hole becomes slightly positively or negatively charged, it will more strongly attract matter of the opposite charge, accrete it, and become more neutral. Thus, neutrally charged black holes are expected to be much more common than charged black holes.</p> <h2 id="spin-vs-charge">Spin vs. Charge</h2> <p>A summary of the types of black holes according to their spin and charge properties is hown in the table below.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>Not Charged</th> <th>Charged</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Not Rotating</td> <td>Swarzchild</td> <td>Reissner–Nordström</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Rotating</td> <td>Kerr</td> <td>Kerr–Newman</td> </tr> </tbody> </table>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="cosmology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some of the simplest and most powerful objects in the cosmos.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cherenkov Radiation</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-cherenkov-radiation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cherenkov Radiation"/><published>2022-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-cherenkov-radiation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-cherenkov-radiation/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/thumb_cherenkov-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/thumb_cherenkov-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/thumb_cherenkov-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/thumb_cherenkov.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Visible Cherenkov radiation inside the Advanced Test Reactor at Idaho National Laboratory.<d-footnote>https://www.energy.gov/ne/articles/cherenkov-radiation-explained</d-footnote>. </div> <p>Similarly to the “boom” heard as an aircraft moves at supersonic speeds through air, Cherenkov radiation occurs due to charged paricles moving at, not supersonic, but superluminal (faster than the speed of light) speeds through a dielectric (poor electrical insulator, can be polarised electrically) medium.</p> <h2 id="physics">Physics</h2> <p>Firstly, we note that the universal speed limit set by light is strictly true of light moving through a vacuum, however, within a medium it is entirely possible for matter to travel faster than light. As the charged particle moves through the dielectric medium, it excites the electrons in the nearby particles of that medium. When those electrons of nearby medium particles return to their ground state, they emit a photon wavefront in all directions. If the particle is moving through the medium faster than the speed of light in that medium, then these wavefronts will concentrate into a conical shape. Many particles doing this at any given time will give the appearance of a “glow” from their source within the medium. This is analagous to the sonic boom produced by something moving through air at supersonic speeds, as shown in Figure 1.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/sboom-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/sboom-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/sboom-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/sboom.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Sonic boom produced by a supersonic object in air<d-footnote>Courses.lumenlearning.com. 2022. 17.8 Shock Waves | University Physics Volume 1. [online] Available at: [Accessed 16 July 2022].</d-footnote>. </div> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <p>The most ubiquitous example of Cherenkov radiation is that as a result of operational nuclear reactors housed within an open pool of liquid water. In such cases, high velocity electrons are released as products of nuclear fission which can move faster than the speed of light in water (0.75*c). Escaping the confides of the reactor, these electrons interact with the electrons of the water molecules to produce optical light (bluish in colour) - refer to Figure 2.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/reactor-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/reactor-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/reactor-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/cherenkov_radiation/reactor.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Cherenkov radiation due to electrons moving through water within an open pool nuclear reactor<d-footnote>Nature.com. 2019. How a particle racing through a vacuum leaves a trail of blue light. [online] Available at: [Accessed 16 July 2022].</d-footnote>. </div>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="nuclear-physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Linking supersonic booms to glowing nuclear facilities.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Universal Measuring Sticks</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-universal-measuring-sticks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Measuring Sticks"/><published>2022-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-universal-measuring-sticks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-universal-measuring-sticks/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/thumb_cepheid-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/thumb_cepheid-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/thumb_cepheid-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/thumb_cepheid.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Cepheid variable, RS Pupis, one of the brightest in the Milky Way galaxy<d-footnote>https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cepheid_variable</d-footnote>. </div> <h2 id="cepheid-variables">Cepheid Variables</h2> <h3 id="apparent-brightness-vs-absolute-brightness">Apparent Brightness vs. Absolute Brightness</h3> <p>If all stars in the universe were the same, then could easily deduce their distance from Earth similarly to how we humans can gauge distances to a common candle - we know how bright it should be near us, so anything less than that must be due to its distance away from us. The brightness of a star from a set distance (10 parsecs or 32.6 light-years) is known as its absolute brightness<d-footnote>Howell, E. (2017) Brightest Stars: Luminosity &amp; Magnitude Oct 12, 2017. Available at: https://www.space.com/21640-star-luminosity-and-magnitude.html (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022). </d-footnote>; conversely, how bright the star is to us from Earth’s perspective (i.e., possibly more or less than 10 parsecs) is its apparent brightness. We always know a star’s apparent brightness by simply observing it, yet its absolute brightness is more difficult to deduce - once both are known, the distance to the star can be found.</p> <h3 id="period-luminosity-relationship">Period-Luminosity Relationship</h3> <p>Some stars, known as Cepheid variables, exhibit regular oscillations in their absolute brightness - the period of which reveals the star’s absolute brightness. This phenomenon was discovered between 1900-1910 by Henrietta Leavitt, an American astronomer (CSIRO, 2022) (Figure 1). By finding such stars, the distances to them, and hence the galaxy they may reside within, can also be deduced.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/period_luminosity-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/period_luminosity-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/period_luminosity-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/period_luminosity.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Period-luminosity relationship of Cepheid variables<d-footnote>CSIRO (2022) Cepheid Variable Stars &amp; Distance Determination Available at: https://www.atnf.csiro.au/outreach/education/senior/astrophysics/variable_cepheids.html (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022).</d-footnote>. </div> <h2 id="type-1a-supernovae">Type 1A Supernovae</h2> <p>Somewhat similarly, particular types of supernova, known as Type IA Supernovae (SNIa), exhibit time-related relationships with the decay of their brightness which can then be used to determine their absolute brightness. SNIa are dissimilar to traditional supernovae in that they do not occur due to the collapse of a massive star. Instead, SNIa are believed to occur as a result of a white dwarf star stealing plasma from a co-orbiting star within its binary system until the white dwarf crosses the Chandrasekhar limit (Cosmos, 2022). The Chandrasekhar limit is definted as the mass of a star that is 1.44 times that of our Sun - a limit, which if exceeded, will cause a star to collapse (including existing white dwarfs)<d-footnote>Encyclopedia Britannica (2021) Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar Dec 22, 2021. Available at: https://www.britannica.com/biography/Subrahmanyan-Chandrasekhar (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022).</d-footnote>. SNIa are the brightest type of supernovae - able to outshine their entire host galaxy during their short existence (Figure 2). The decay of the SNIa’s brightness is measured over a period of 15 days from the maximuim light in the B band (445 nm wavelength midpoint).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/snia-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/snia-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/snia-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/universal_measuring_sticks/snia.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: An SNIa (SN 1994D) in a spiral galaxy about 55 million light-years from the Solar System in the Virgo constellation (NGC 4526)<d-footnote>Cosmos - The SAO Encyclopedia of Astronomy (2022) Type Ia Supernova Available at: https://astronomy.swin.edu.au/cosmos/t/Type+Ia+Supernova (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022).</d-footnote>. </div>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="astronomy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How distances are measured in the vast, unreachable space around us.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reviewing ‘Rocket Men’</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/book-rocket-men/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reviewing ‘Rocket Men’"/><published>2022-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/book-rocket-men</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/book-rocket-men/"><![CDATA[<p><b>9/10</b></p> <p>‘Rocket Men’ throws you into the midst of the space race between the United States of America and the Soviet Union, summer of 1968. The focus on the astronauts (Frank Borman, James Lovell Jr. and William Anders), their families, and the growing risks of their goal to put a man on the moon before 1970, sets the stage for the gripping story of how a will to win transformed into a will to survive for Apollo 8.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books"/><category term="spaceflight"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A will to win and a will to survive.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Oberth Effect</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-oberth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Oberth Effect"/><published>2022-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-oberth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-oberth/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/thumb_oberth-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/thumb_oberth-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/thumb_oberth-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/thumb_oberth.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Second stage of the launch of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) taking advantage of the Oberth effect<d-footnote>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7nT7JGZMbtM&amp;ab_channel=NASA</d-footnote>. </div> <h2 id="maths">Maths</h2> <p>The Oberth effect maximises the efficiency of a rocket burn by considering the instantaneous kinetic energy of the rocket at particular moments during its flight and selecting the most suitable time to burn. This concept can be understood by analysing the equation for the kinetic energy of a body at a given instantaneous moment.</p> \[\Delta KE = {1/2} m v^2\] <p>Now, the change in kinetic energy between two instantaneous moments (e.g., from beginning to the end of a burn) can be expressed.</p> \[\Delta KE = {KE}_2 - {KE}_1\] <p>Also assuming that the change in mass of the craft is negligible (i.e., \({m_1} \approx {m_2} \approx m\))</p> \[\Delta KE = {1/2} m ( {v_2}^2 - {v_1}^2 )\] <p>Now, taking the value \({1/2} m\) as an arbitrary scalar, the function above can be graphed in 3D as shown below<d-footnote>https://www.math3d.org/</d-footnote>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_diagonal.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_straight-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/oberth_graph_straight.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Three dimensional graph of the change in kinetic energy with respect to the speed of the object before and after an engine burn. </div> <p>As illustrated above, for a constant change of velocity (i.e., constant \(\Delta v = v_2 - v_1\) where \(v_2 &gt; v_1\)), the change in kinetic energy is greatest when the individual values of \(v_1\) and \(v_2\) are larger. For example, let the change in velocity be \(\Delta v = 1 {m/s}\) (assume unit mass of 1 kg). If the initial velocity is \(1 {m/s}\) and the final velocity is \(2 {m/s}\), the change in kinetic energy is \(3J\). However, if the initial velocity is \(2 {m/s}\) and the final velocity is \(3 {m/s}\), the change in kinetic energy is \(5J\). This example shows that equal changes in velocity with different starting conditions can produce different changes in kinetic energy (i.e., \(3J\) compared to \(5J\)). That is, a greater change in kinetic energy is possible, using the same change in velocity, when the change in velocity occurs at higher values. In summary, for a fixed amount of rocket fuel (i.e., fixed change in velocity, \(\Delta v\)), a greater change in overall kinetic energy of the rocket can be achieved by beginning the burn at a higher initial velocity.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <p>On 25 December, 2021 at 1:20pm ACDT, the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) launched from French Guiana aboard the Ariane 5 launch vehicle. However, at about T+08m:04s, the rocket and payload began losing altitude as shown in the altitude vs. distance travelled graph below<d-footnote>NASA (2021) James Webb Space Telescope Launch — Official NASA Broadcast Dec 25, 2021. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7nT7JGZMbtM&amp;t=6710s&amp;ab_channel=NASA (Accessed: Jan 03, 2022).</d-footnote>. By losing altitude, the craft traded some gravitational potential energy for some extra kinetic energy - increasing its speed. Now at a higher initial velocity than it would have been without the energy trade, the rocket began burning its engines for a specific change in velocity. The total kinetic energy increase was more efficient due to the engine burn at higher initial speed (Oberth effect). Utilising the Oberth effect, the Ariane 5 achieved such a fuel efficient payload orbit injection that the JWST now has significantly more propellant than expected to sustain its exploration mission. This extra propellant is expected to extend the lifetime of the JWST far beyond its initially expected 10 years.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/jwst_oberth-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/jwst_oberth-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/jwst_oberth-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/oberth/jwst_oberth.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Altitude versus curvilinear distance for the launch of the James Webb Space Telescope. </div>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="astrodynamics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why going down first helps you go higher.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Size of the Observable Universe</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-size-universe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Size of the Observable Universe"/><published>2022-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-size-universe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2022/tutorial-size-universe/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/size_universe/thumb_size_universe-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/size_universe/thumb_size_universe-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/size_universe/thumb_size_universe-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/size_universe/thumb_size_universe.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The edges of the universe<d-footnote>https://nineplanets.org/questions/how-big-is-the-universe/</d-footnote>. </div> <p>The size of the observable universe is a more complex idea than it appears at face value. It is widely known that the universe is approximately 13.8 billion years old. From this knowledge, it is logical to assume our observable universe is 13.8 billion light years in radius in all directions. However, our true observable universe is approximately 46.5 billion light years in radius (or about 93 billion light years in diameter). The reason for this discrepancy in initial logic (13.8 Bly) and scientific fact (46.5 Bly) is due to a battle between light and space.</p> <h2 id="an-expanding-observable-universe">An Expanding Observable Universe</h2> <p>Lets assume our universe is a flat piece of latex placed on a table. Now assume we paint galaxies on the piece of latex and that their motion <i>through/on</i> the paper is too miniscule to notice. Watching the universe from our perspective, continuous emissions of light from these galaxies are travelling through the universe at a fixed speed (the speed of light). Using this idea, it’s reasonable to imagine an imaginary circle around each galaxy which represents the visible range around that galaxy. That is, light can only travel so far in the time it has been given to travel (i.e., since we painted them on the latex) - and hence as time continues, this visible range of each galaxy grows at the speed of light. This expansion of visible range, due to the fixed speed of light and continuous flow of time, implies that more and more of the universe becomes visible with time - i.e., an expanding observable universe.</p> <h2 id="a-contracting-observable-universe">A Contracting Observable Universe</h2> <p>The reason why the true size of the observable universe is larger than the expected value of 13.8 Bly in radius is because the universe is expanding (discovered by Edwin Hubble in 1929). This rate of expansion, over the 13.8 billion year age of the universe equates to about 33 billion light years of additional space in all directions. Thus, the true size of our visible universe is approximately 13.8+33 Bly = 46.8 Bly in radius<d-footnote>Encyclopedia Brittanica (2013) Know about the concept of the observable universe and on measuring the observable universe within the whole universe Feb 26, 2013. Available At: https://www.britannica.com/video/185400/universe (Accessed: Jan 15, 2022).</d-footnote>. Importantly, this expansion occurs everywhere in the universe as it expands into itself. Referring to the latex universe analogy, this could be represented as stretching the latex - the galaxies aren’t moving (remember our assumption from earlier) but the space between them is expanding. The effect of an expanding universe is contrary to its name as it pushes galaxies apart - reducing their observable regions. Additionally, the rate of expansion exceeds the speed of light - meaning that even though the universe is physically becoming larger, galaxies are being pushed further apart and hence our observable region is becoming smaller.</p> <h2 id="summary">Summary</h2> <p>The rate of the expansion of space exceeds the speed of light. Therefore, even though the universe is becoming physically larger due to its expansion, this also causes galaxies to be pushed further apart faster than their light travels to each other. Therefore, our observable universe is becoming smaller, but the space it occupies is becoming larger.</p> <h2 id="extra-reading">Extra Reading</h2> <p>The real kicker of this concept is that the expansion of the universe is accelerating (2011 Novel Prize in Physics: Saul Perlmutter, Brian Schmidt, Adam Reiss). Therefore, there will come a time (and a distance away from us), where galaxies at that distance are moving away from us (due to the expansion of space between us and them) faster than the speed of light. When this occurs, the light from such galaxies will slowly dim into nothingness and they will be lost to us forever (assuming the universe never begins contracting).</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="cosmology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A battle between light and space.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buffer Overflow Protection</title><link href="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2021/tutorial-buffer-overflow-prot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buffer Overflow Protection"/><published>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2021/tutorial-buffer-overflow-prot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://patrickcap.github.io/blog/2021/tutorial-buffer-overflow-prot/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/thumb_buffer_overflow_prot-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/thumb_buffer_overflow_prot-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/thumb_buffer_overflow_prot-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/thumb_buffer_overflow_prot.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Stopping the overflow<d-footnote>https://www.thespruce.com/inexpensive-worm-bin-from-plastic-buckets-2540077</d-footnote>. </div> <p>Below is a list of various methods to avoid buffer overflows from occurring - more specifically using C language.</p> <h2 id="avoid-unsafe-functions">Avoid Unsafe Functions</h2> <p>Functions such as gets(), sprintf(), strcpy(), and strcat() are unsafe because they all encourage some form of stack frame overwrite that can induce a buffer overflow. For example, strcpy() will copy a string into a buffer until the null character is found - regardless of the declared size of the buffer - easily inducing overflow if the user is not conscious of their buffer and input size.</p> <p>Users should avoid these functions if possible and look for alternatives such as their corresponding ‘n’ versions: fgets(), snprinft(), strncpy, and strncat(). These alternatives require an extra argument being the number of characters (or bytes) that the user wishes to be interacted with - rather than simply relying on the presence of a null character or not. This forces the user to know the bounds in which they are working.</p> <h2 id="bound-checking">Bound Checking</h2> <p>In addition to the practices mentioned previously, users should also be aware of the bounds of their program and the limitations of the functions they are using. For example, while the ‘n’ functions listed above require more information, if the user supplies incorrect information, they will do nothing to prevent a buffer overflow (e.g. giving the wrong number of characters). Due to this, it is imperative that the user is aware of how these functions work and what the limitations of their buffers are to prevent an overflow. I can tell you from experience that the most overlooked source of overflow is the null character. It is very often not accounted for in expected buffer sizes and hence is often the cause of 1-byte overflows which are equally as dangerous as a full stack overflow.</p> <h2 id="canaries">Canaries</h2> <p>Just as canaries were kept in coal mines to warn for the presence of toxic gases, the same method can be used in computer memory to warn for the presence of a buffer overflow. The concept is quite simple - place a known value in between the buffer (what can cause overflow) and the stack frame metadata (what we want to protect) (refer to Figure 1).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/canary-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/canary-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/canary-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/tutorials/buffer_overflow_prot/canary.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Canary location to identify stack buffer overflow. </div> <p>Since the value is known to the machine and not to the attacker, the machine can simply check if the value has been modified after the callee function finishes and if it has, the program exits safely (overflow), and if not, it continues as normal (no overflow). The security of this defence depends on the value of the canary chosen. If the value is easy to guess or can be created naturally as a memory location - this defence is weakened. The value of the canary should be changed for each function call (to avoid it being brute-forced) and should be difficult to guess for an attacker.</p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Capaldo</name></author><category term="tutorials"/><category term="cybersecurity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to protect programs written in C from buffer overflow.]]></summary></entry></feed>